Charles Tournemire Collection
Music Division, Library of Congress
Guides to Special Collections in the Music Division of the Library of Congress
Charles Tournemire Collection circa 1868-1962 (bulk 1900-1936)
ML31.T68
Tournemire, Charles, 1870-1939
67 items 9 containers 5.0 linear feet
Music Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Charles Tournemire was a French composer, organist, and teacher. The collection chiefly consists of holograph, manuscript and printed music by Tournemire and other composers. In addition, the collection contains librettos, a scrapbook, books and a journal.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
People
Tournemire, Charles, 1870-1939--Manuscripts.; Tournemire, Charles, 1870-1939.; Tournemire, Charles, 1870-1939.; Tournemire, Charles, 1870-1939. Sang de la sirène.; Tournemire, Charles, 1870-1939. Selections.
Subjects
Composers--France.; Music--Manuscripts--20th century.; Organists--France.
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift; Alice Tournemire; 1998.
Accruals
No further accruals are expected.
Transfers
Two books from the collection that bear Tournemire’s signature have been transferred to the Library of Congress general collections. They are La Bible d’Amiens by Ruskin and L’évolution divine du sphinx au Christ by Schuré.
Access and Restrictions
The Charles Tournemire Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Music Division prior to visiting in order to determine whether the desired materials will be available at that time.
Certain restrictions to use or copying of materials may apply.
Biographical Note
Charles Tournemire, a composer, organist, and teacher, was born in Bordeaux, France, on Jan. 22, 1870. He was appointed organist of the church of St. Pierre in Bordeaux at the age of eleven. After studying at the Bordeaux Conservatoire, he transferred to the Paris Conservatoire at the age of sixteen, where he studied the piano with Bériot and harmony with Taudou. Around 1889, he joined César Franck's organ class and in 1891 Tournemire won first prize for organ in Charles-Marie Widor's class. After working briefly at Saint-Nicolas-du-Chardonnet, he succeeded Gabriel Pierné as organist at the Basilique Sainte Clotilde, a post he held for the rest of his life. Between 1900 and 1904 he composed his first five symphonies. He achieved his first major recognition as a composer when he won the concours musicale de las ville de Paris for his choral work Le sang de la siréne in 1904.
In 1908, Tournemire married the sister of the wife of Josephin "Sâr" Péladan, a French mystic who was the founder of the Ordre de Rose-Croix in Paris. Tournemire began immersing himself in nineteenth century French mystical writers, such as Hello, Huysmans, and Péladan. Beginning in the late 1920s, Tournemire increasingly withdrew from the musical establishment becoming heavily involved with not only mystical writers, but medieval architecture and early Christian spirituality.
Tournemire composed three more symphonies after the First World War, none of which were performed in his lifetime. In 1919, he became professor of chamber music at the Paris Conservatoire where he also taught organ improvisation. Tournemire was an influential teacher whose students included Maurice Duruflé, Jean Langlais, and Daniel Lesur, among others.
After 1921, many of his best compositions were written for the church. He wrote the immense L'orgue mystique (1927-1932) which was a cycle of fifty-one organ suites, one for every Sunday of the church year, each based on the appropriate plainsong. In 1931, Tournemire recorded five organ improvisations at Sainte Clotilde. These were later transcribed from the phonograph recordings by Maurice Duruflé and are among his best known works. His last composition was the opera Il poverello di Assisi (1937-1938) based on a text by "Sâr" Péladan.
The precise cause and date of his death are uncertain. He died at Arcachon around Nov. 4, 1939.
Scope and Content Note
The collection primarily consists of manuscript and printed music, but also includes librettos, a scrapbook, books, and one issue of a journal.
The music includes items by Tournemire and by other composers. The Tournemire materials include six holographs, including an arrangement for piano (four hands) of the First symphony by Raoul Moreau, three manuscripts, and eight printed scores. There are two additional Tournemire holographs, one is an arrangement of the sixth suite from Walther's Hortulus chelicus, and the other a transcription of Frescobaldi's Toccata per l'Elevazione. The printed scores by other composers include items from the Ecole classique de l’Orgue series, edited by A. Guilmant.
Additional materials include two librettos for Tournemire works, a lyric sheet of a poem by Verlaine, and a scrapbook entitled Le sang de la siréne, after Tournemire's prize-winning composition.
Six books came with the collection, four of which are annotated and one printed especially for Tournemire. Two books were transferred to the Library of Congress general collections (see "Transfers" above).
Organization of the Charles Tournemire Collection
The Charles Tournemire Collection is organized in five series:
Music, circa 1868-1962
Librettos
Scrapbook, 1904, 1909
Books, circa 1899-1923
Journal, 1928
http://lccn.loc.gov/2006568223
Container List
- Music, circa 1868-1962, undated (Box 1-7)
  - Music by Charles Tournemire, 1899-1962, undated (Box 1-2, 4-6)
    Original compositions, including manuscripts and printed scores, and arrangements and transcriptions.
    Arranged by opus number.
    - Manuscripts
      - 1re Symphonie romantique, op. 18 bis, Holograph in ink; 86 p.; Arrangement for piano, four hands, by Raoul Moreau.; According to Fauquet (p. 32) it was unfinished. (Box-folder 2/1)
      - Poème [mystique] pour piano, op. 33, Manuscript in ink; 40 p.; Dedicated “A madame Charles Tournemire.”; For information about other dedications, see Fauquet, p. 27. (Box-folder 2/2)
      - (Chryséis) Les Dieux sont morts, drame lyrique, op. 42 (fragments for the concert performance), Holograph in ink, 122 p.; At end: 1912.; See Fauquet, p. 67. (Box-folder 4/1)
      - La Legénde de Tristan, op. 53, Manuscript in ink; 25 p.; Vocal part for Iseut. (Box-folder 2/3)
      - La Legénde de Tristan, op. 53, Manuscript (holograph?) in ink; 6 p.; Vocal part for Tristan.; Incomplete. (Box-folder 2/4)
      - Fantasie symphonique pour orgue, op. 64, Holograph in ink; 18 p.; Dedicated to Marcel Dupré. At end: 25 Avril 1934.; See Fauquet, p. 43. (Box-folder 2/5)
      - Symphonie-choral d’orgue, op. 69, Holograph in ink; 44 p.; At end: 22 Novembre 1935.; See Fauquet, p. 48. (Box-folder 2/6)
      - Symphonie sacrée pour orgue, op. 71, Holograph in ink, 44 p.; At end: 15 Février 1936.; See Fauquet, p. 48-49. (Box-folder 2/7)
      - Deux fresques symphoniques sacrées pour orgue, op. 75 and op. 76, Holograph in ink, 14 + 23 p.; At end: 4 Novembre 1938; 22 Février 1939.; See Fauquet, p. 49-50. (Box-folder 2/8)
    - Printed Music
      - Pièce symphonique pour grand orgue, op. 16. Paris: Schola Cantorum, [1899], Répertoire moderne de Musique vocale et d’Orgue, no. 17. (Box-folder 2/11)
      - Suite de Morceaux pour grand-orgue, op. 19 (Toccata, Interludes). Paris: Pérégally & Parvy, 1900, Toccata with annotations.; Interludes with the following dedication on the title page: “A Madame Juhel-Rénoy.” (Box-folder 2/12)
      - Sagesse, poème pour chant et piano, op. 34. Lyon: Janin, 1921 (Box-folder 2/13)
      - Triple choral pour orgue, op. 41. Lyon: Janin, 1912, With annotations. (Box-folder 2/14)
      - Triple choral pour orgue, op. 41. Paris: Schola Cantorum, Procure générale de musique, [1962], Orgue et Liturgie, no. 54. (Box-folder 2/15)
      - Les Dieux sont morts, drame lyrique, op. 42. Paris: Choudens, 1921, Piano-vocal score; Title page and the end missing.; Annotations. (Box-folder 1/1)
      - Suite evocatrice pour grand orgue, op. 74. Paris: Bornemann, 1938, With annotations. (Box-folder 2/16)
      - L’orgue mystique, op. 55, 56, 57. Cycle de Noël, op. 55. Paris: Heugel, 1928-1930 (Box-folder 5/1)
      - Cycle de Paques, op. 56. Paris: Heugel, 1928-1930 (Box 6)
      - Cycle après la Pentacôte, op. 57. I: No. 26-38. Paris: Heugel, 1928-1932 (Box-folder 5/2)
      - Cycle après la Pentacôte, op. 57. II: No. 39-51. Paris: Heugel, 1934-1936 (Box-folder 5/3)
    - Arrangements and Transcriptions
      - Walther, Johann Jakob. 6e suite de l’Hortulus chelicus, accompagment arrangée par Ch. Tournemire, op. 13. Violin part., Arranger’s holograph in ink; [3] p.; The movements are not the same as the ones in the score (see Fauquet, p. 65).; Printed violin part, movements: Allemande and Gigue. (Box-folder 2/9)
      - Frescobaldi, Girolamo. Toccata per l’Elevazione, Manuscript in ink; [2] p.; Transcribed by Ch. Tournemire (?). (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Music by Other Composers, circa 1868-circa 1938, undated (Box 1, 3, 7)
    Printed scores, including several from the series Ecole classique de l’Orgue.
    Arranged alphabetically by composer or title.
    - Bach, Johann Sebastian. Chorals-Préludes, Ier Livre. Paris: Heugel, [19--], Annotations pp. 14, 30-31. (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Bach, Johann Sebastian. Chorals-Préludes, 4er Livre. Paris: Heugel, [19--], Annotations pp. 58-59. (Box-folder 3/2)
    - Bach, Johann Sebastian. Chorals-Préludes, 5e Livre. Paris: Heugel, [19--], Annotations pp. 4-5, 41, 64. (Box-folder 3/3)
    - Buxtehude, Dietrich. Werke für orgel, v. 1. Leipzig: Breitkopf & Härtel, 1903-1904, Title page and introduction missing.; Annotated (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Buxtehude, Dietrich. Werke für orgel, v. 2. Leipzig: Breitkopf & Härtel, 1903-1904, Annotated. (Box-folder 3/5)
    - Cabanilles, Iohannis. Opera omnia, vol. 1. Barcelona: Biblioteca de Cataluña, 1927, Inscribed by the editor Hygini Anglès to Ch. Tournemire, Paris, 4.3.1930.; Annotations mainly pp. 41-43. (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Cabanilles, Iohannis. Opera omnia, vol. 2. Barcelona: Institut d’estudis Catalans, Biblioteca de Catalunya, 1933, Inscribed by the editor Hygini Anglès to Ch. Tournemire, Barcelona, 15. XII. 1933. (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Cabanilles, Iohannis. Opera omnia, vol. 3. Barcelona: Institut d’estudis Catalans, Biblioteca de Catalunya, 1936 (Box-folder 1/6)
    - Franck, Cèsar. 6 pièces d’orgue. Paris: Durand, 1868-1890?, Missing pp. 79-90.; Annotations pp. 57-67. (Box-folder 3/6)
    - Frescobaldi, Girolamo. Fiori musicali. Paris: Senart, 1922 (Box-folder 7/1)
    - Frescobaldi, Girolamo. Sammlung von orgelsätzen. Leipzig: Breikopf & Härtel, 1889? (Box-folder 7/2)
    - Frescobaldi, Girolamo. Toccata XII. Paris: Hérelle, [19--] (Box-folder 7/3)
    - Griguy, Nicolas de. Oeuvres d’orgue. London: Schott, 1904, Inscribed by the editor Alexandre Guilmant to Ch. Tournemire, 1906. (Box-folder 7/4)
    - Liszt, Franz. Zwölf Kirchen-Chor-Gesänge mit Orgelbegleitung; no. 12: Pro Papa: Dominus conservet eum. Leipzig: C. F. Kahnt, [189-?] (Box-folder 7/5)
    - Mathey, Paul. Ante et post praedicationem, op.2. Zwei Stücke für Orgel und Violine (ohne Obligatespedal), 2 v. Zürich; Leipzig: Gebrüder Hug, 1938?, Inscribed by the author to Ch. Tournemire, 1938. (Box-folder 7/6)
    - Matthews, Edmund. Chorale prelude on “St. Mary” for the organ. London: Novello, 1933, Inscribed by the author to Ch. Tournemire, 1936. (Box-folder 7/7)
    - Matthews, Edmund. Interlude on “Strength and Stay” for the organ. London: Novello, 1933, Inscribed by the author to Ch. Tournemire, 1936. (Box-folder 7/8)
    - Ropartz, Joseph Guy. Intermède. Paris: Schola Cantorum, [189-?], Répertoire moderne de Musique vocale et d’Orgue, no 4 bis. (Box-folder 7/9)
    - Ropartz, Joseph Guy. Sur un thème Breton. Paris: Schola Cantorum, 1900, Annotated. (Box-folder 7/10)
    - Items in the Ecole classique de l’orgue/A. Guilmant series:
      - Bruhns, Nicolas. Choral Nun komm, der heiden Heiland. Paris: Durand, circa 1900, Ecole classique de l’orgue/A. Guilmant; no.3. (Box-folder 7/11)
      - Buxtehude, Dietrich. Fugue en Ut. Paris: Durand, circa 1900, Ecole classique de l’orgue/A. Guilmant; no.22.; Annotated. (Box-folder 7/12)
      - Buxtehude, Dietrich. Prélude et Fugue en La. Paris: Durand, circa 1900, Ecole classique de l’orgue/A. Guilmant; no.2.; Annotated. (Box-folder 7/13)
      - Frescobaldi, Girolamo. Fugue en Sol mineur. Paris: Durand, circa 1900, Ecole classique de l’orgue/A. Guilmant; no.70.; Annotated. (Box-folder 7/14)
      - Krebs, Johann Ludwig. Fugue en Sol. Paris: Durand, circa 1900, Ecole classique de l’orgue/A. Guilmant; no.15.; Annotated. (Box-folder 7/15)
      - Murschhauser, F. X. A. Praeambulum du 3e ton, Arpeggiata, Fuga. Paris: Durand, circa 1900, Ecole classique de l’orgue/A. Guilmant; no.16. (Box-folder 7/16)
      - Scheidt, Samuel. Cantilena anglica fortunae. Paris: Durand, circa 1900, Ecole classique de l’orgue/A. Guilmant; no.14.; Annotated. (Box-folder 7/17)
      - Sweelinck, Jan Pieters. Fantasie en Ré mineur. Paris: Durand, circa 1900, Ecole classique de l’orgue/A. Guilmant; no.6.; Annotated. (Box-folder 7/18)
      - Walther, Johann Gottfried. Prélude et fugue en La majeur. Paris: Durand, circa 1900, Ecole classique de l’orgue/A. Guilmant; no.4.; Title page missing.; Annotated. (Box-folder 7/19)
      - Concert historique d’orgue / revus par Alexandre Guilmant. Paris: Durand, 1889?, Annotated. (Box-folder 7/20)
      - Unidentified. Compositions for organ, pp. 105-112.; Plate number: A. G. 104.; Annotated. (Box-folder 7/21)
- Librettos (Box 1, 8)
  Manuscript librettos and lyric sheet for compositions by Tournemire.
  - Nittetis, tragédie lyrique en 3 actes et 7 tableaux, op. 30. Acte I., Holograph in ink; around 120 p. (Box-folder 8/3)
  - Nittetis, tragédie lyrique en 3 actes et 7 tableaux, op. 30. Acte II., Holograph in ink; around 120 p. (Box-folder 8/4)
  - Nittetis, tragédie lyrique en 3 actes et 7 tableaux, op. 30. Acte III., Holograph in ink; around 120 p. (Box-folder 8/5)
  - Sagesse, op. 34; poem by Paul Verlaine, Manuscript in ink; [1], 4 leaves (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Trilogie Faust - Don Quichotte - Saint François d’Assise, op. 52, Holograph in ink; 16 + 25 + 14 leaves (Box-folder 1/2)
- Scrapbook, 1904, 1909 (Box 1)
  Articles and correspondence about Le sang de la siréne, by Tournemire (1904).
  - Le Sang de la Sirène (title on the cover), 1904, 1909, 200 p.; Articles on Tournemire’s Le sang de la siréne, op. 27, 1904; pp. 1-29.; Letters of congratulations, business cards, postcards, 1904 and 1909; pp. 30-99.; Laid in: letter from 1909 (p. 83), printed report on the competition concours musicale de las ville de Paris, 1900-1903, Paris 1904. (Box-folder 1/7)
- Books, circa 1899-1923, undated (Box 8, 9)
  Two books were transferred to the Library of Congress general collections.
  Arranged alphabetically by author.
  - Bédier, Joseph. Le roman de Tristan et Iseut. Paris: L’Edition d’Art, 1914., At end of book: Exemplaire imprimé pour Charles Tournemire. (Box-folder 9/3)
  - Emmerich, Anne-Catherine. La douloureuse passion de Notre-seigneur Jésus-Christ. Tournai: Casterman, [18-- ], Annotated. (Box-folder 8/1)
  - Pauphilet, Albert. La queste du Saint Graal. Paris: Les éditions de la Sirène, 1923, Annotated. (Box-folder 9/2)
  - Theocritus. Œuvres complètes de Théocrite. Paris: Garnier frères, 1899, Annotated. (Box-folder 9/3)
  - Ruskin, John. La Bible d’Amiens. Paris: Societé du mercure de France, 1904, Transferred to the Library of Congress general collections.
  - Schuré, Eduard. L’évolution divine du sphinx au Christ. Paris: Perrin, 1921, Transferred to the Library of Congress general collections.
- Journal, 1928 (Box 8)
  Contains one issue.
  - Cahiers Rhodaniens. January 1928, Inscribed by Albert Pauphilet to Ch. Tournemire.; Annotated. (Box-folder 8/2)